The hing cycle is a kind of heartbeat
for the Bitcoin economy and market.
People learn to hold coins and not trade
them. It's hard to arbitrage something
which is volatile. But there's a lot of
people who are looking at it from the
outside who don't know a lot of the
details, right? So, it's obvious to us,
but maybe it's not so obvious to the
market. It's been, you know, a market
cycle that has seen Bitcoin rise while
the rest of the assets have shrunk in
market share. Actually, once computers
are still a few decades away, if nothing
changes, they might be able to take lost
coins or Satoshi's coins. What was your
first reaction to the email that you
received from Satoshi?
>> If you could go back to the day when you
received the email from Satoshi, knowing
what you know now, you can ask him three
questions.
>> Well, I I've been curious.
>> It's a great privilege to honor our next
guest, Adam Beck, an OG in the Bitcoin
space. He is the co-founder of
Blockstream, but equally importantly, he
is cited in the original Satoshi
Nakamoto white paper for Bitcoin. Adam's
early work on hash laid the foundations
for the mining process we know today and
the proof of work system that we know
today. He's been dubbed or perhaps
considered the real Satoshi.
I don't know about that. But uh it was a
certainly interesting experience and
ride getting kind of instant fame in
Bitcoin relatively early on because of
the hash connection and I was somebody
that was interested in and implemented
some of the previous more centralized
electronic cash systems. So certainly
you know became very interested in
Bitcoin as well. What was your first
impression? Not impression but reaction
to the email that you received from
Satoshi?
>> Yeah, so I get a lot of emails of you
know every month or two from people
using some of the open source source
code I've implemented or using some kind
of applied paper and hash was one of
those and so you know it felt like
another one of those. I thought Toshi
Nakamoto is the real guy's name
developer or researcher and um
so but you know I was involved in the
attempt to build an electronic cash
system after digash the previous system
had failed and the reason it failed
wasn't technological exactly but it was
because it was centralized and the
central database allowed you to verify
the coins were valid and the company
failed. So then the coins you might have
became unspendable. And so you know the
people that were interested in
electronic cash on the cipher punks list
the way they reacted to that is to draw
lessons that you know well electronic
cash is very cool. We want to see it
come back. Uh we need to solve a
decentralization problem. You know it's
centralized it failed. So we need a
decentralized solution. That's very
technically challenging.
>> Is it is it so but correct me if wrong
but your original proof of work concept
was not intended for money right? It was
for email.
right? It was as a kind of postage
stamp. Now what you know that was in the
context of the digit cache system which
had recently failed at that time and so
you know the obvious thing for the
anti-spam problem in a remaer context
where you don't know who's sending it
>> would be to use the electronic cache
system. But given that the candidate
then had failed and there was no clear
technology solution to implement a
decentralized one. Yeah.
>> I tried to solve a simpler problem which
became a postage stamp. Interestingly,
within a day of posting that, multiple
people independently observed its
potential use to solve one of the
problems of a decentralized system,
which is how do you get money into it?
So, it brought in the concepts
immediately that well, you could mine
it. And so hash became part of the
design ideas like Boney and Bit Gold in
uh 1998. So a year later
>> and Hal Finny's RP power in 2004 and
then of course Bitcoin starting in 2008
when Satoshi started emailing people.
>> Um I have one more question before I
pass it over to Bonnie. Suppose we were
to live on a desert island in a complete
anarchy where there's no centralized
government, where there's no governing
authority. It's just we do whatever we
want. But we do need some sort of medium
of exchange in order to operate this
society, if you want to call it that.
What kind of exchange system would you
need for this particular type of
society? Barter? Would it be coinage?
You can't mint coinage because everybody
has a different coin. How would that be
standard unit of currency?
>> Yeah. I mean, I think what you've seen
from human history is that money evolves
as sort of a natural phenomena because
people want to exchange. So they can
exchange in terms of IUS. You know, like
you provided me with some bread, I owe
you for that. I'm producing something
else. I provide it later. But that's
inefficient. say what tends to happen is
people settle on a on a standard good
that's scarce and that's evolved over
time sea shells then gold
uh and now Bitcoin I guess it's the it's
the new improved monetary technology so
I think people look for whatever is
relatively scarce in the environment the
best candidate and they use it they end
up using it for that purpose so on this
hypothetical island that would be what
you know maybe it would be some hard to
find seashells that you have to spend a
lot of time looking for or you know some
some uh commodity like a gold ore or or
something like that and so I think
Bitcoin is really um
>> digital
>> digital gold a digital solution to that
so actually a better hot money
>> if Satoshi would have chosen a slow
decline instead of for your having
that change the balance
>> yeah I mean it's uh it's interesting
question because some parts of Bitcoin
look like they could have had
alternative parameters and still
probably worked and so yeah, you could
certainly have see a uh gradual like a
smooth slope of supply rather than one
that's stepping every four years with
half the supply and half the fresh
supply and so I think coincidentally it
seems that the h havinging cycle is a
kind of heartbeat for the Bitcoin
economy and market. It, you know, it
does seem to continue to affect this the
market cycle even as it represents a
smaller proportion of the coins in
circulation. Now there are almost 20
million and so the drop from you know 6
and a4 to 3 and 1 e is is a smaller uh
drop. So I think how that comes to still
be economically significant is over time
people learn to hold coins and not trade
them. And so the coins that are left uh
that can be reached in the market are
shrinking as in line with the you know
the rate of supply is also shrinking. So
they they stay roughly in line and
that's how you know you can have this
counterintuitive phenomena that
something which is a smaller and smaller
percentage versus supply still have a
very noticeable effect on the market
every h havinging so I think you know it
it could have presumably worked without
the h havinging but the hinging is a
nice kind of economic cycle driver turns
out
>> it's just amazing how the design is so
perfect you know I remember you were
talking about um early days People were
not well people were worried about you
know the blockchain being too
transparent and now you know blockstream
has this liquid that tries to protect
privacy. Now tell me if well if the
original Bitcoin design is for everyone
to see the transaction is that against
the law of Bitcoin? Well, I think you
know I was um because I was familiar
with the previous systems
while they were centralized the academic
cryptographers
had tried to arrive at the idealized or
perfect characteristics for electronic
cash system and of course the technology
wouldn't necessarily be quite able to
meet that but they were able to have
extremely strong confidentiality and
privacy of who was transacting with who.
So, it's really a bearer money with
cryptographic assurance. And it turns
out with a distributed system that
cryptography doesn't work. And so, you
know, there are still ways to make it
work, but they're far more complicated
and less efficient. And so, Bitcoin
doesn't, you know, out of the gate use
those. Um
and so you know I would view the fact
that Bitcoin doesn't bring those
properties in its initial launch really
a technological limitation and not you
know a design intention but you know
that's speculation because so she didn't
explain but I think you know you can see
that even in the Bitcoin paper it's
talking about you know transacting
without a middleman and bearer kind of
cashlike uh properties. right, which are
actually better insured by these
cryptographic mechanisms. It's just that
they are, you know, they're harder and
they're still not, you know, probably
quite at the stage you'd want to deploy
them on Bitcoin, which has a lot of
value on it.
>> So, does that mean we'll see more and
more chains that's being built that
cares more about privacy? Well, I think
what tends to happen is that the
features that you know become available
technologically get added to Bitcoin
either directly in the base layer or in
layer 2s uh where there are trade-offs
that don't quite make sense for the base
layer. So, yeah, I think Bitcoin is, you
know, increasing market share. The new
money coming in, you know, via the ETFs
are kind of the top 10% in terms of
share portfolio minus the top 1%. So
just you know people with a portfolio
that talk to their broker. So I think
they're reallocating shares or gold ETFs
into Bitcoin. All that money is going
into Bitcoin not into the other coins.
And you know the institutions are have
professional managers and and they are
focused on Bitcoin as well. So I think
it's been you know a market cycle that
has seen Bitcoin rise while the rest of
the assets have shrunk in market share.
Actually,
>> if you could go back to the day when you
received the email from Satoshi, knowing
what you know now, you can ask him three
questions.
>> Well, I put I've been curious over time
how he arrived at the solution because,
you know, people had been trying to find
a way to make this work in
2000 in in 1997, 1998 already, right?
And uh so there's a sort of
technological leap between the proof of
work and the scarcity and how to have
the system work without any identity.
Just just that you so you know we
understand how Bitcoin works but it's
kind of a curiosity for me how he
arrived at that idea you know because a
lot of people tried to find a solution
and didn't. Um so that's one thing. Uh,
I think there's some other curiosities
like why 21 million, why not 42 or 10
million?
>> Oh, that's a good question.
>> Um,
yeah. And now I don't think there was
really that much he could have done in
terms of adding privacy technology into
it. You know, I did notice when first
looking at Bitcoin that there was a
potential solution in this 1999 paper
called auditable electronic cash that
that was actually compatible with a
decentralized system. But the coins will
be quite big and so and it's kind of
more esoteric. So maybe he didn't know
about that solution. But um yeah, I
think it's it's been going very well
since and you know with the evolution of
layer 2s and the continued gradual
careful evolution of layer 1 to sort of
add flexibility to develop more types of
layer 2s. Things are uh going as well as
anybody could expect. I think better
even right
>> I'm surprised one of the questions isn't
who are you
>> that's the first thing I would have
asked
>> I would have
>> well I mean at the time I thought that
was his name right so
>> fair enough
>> yeah I mean of course it is it is a
curiosity as to who Soshi might be a
kind of mystery that is you know behind
the currency but
>> your favorite theory as to who it may be
>> I don't know it's like all of the ones
that have been put forward seem to have
some flaw where it's not quite
believable and say,
you know, of course, I know a number of
people that were interested in this
area, like developers and so on, but it
seems like we don't like nobody seems to
know who it is. And of course, there
were people
back in the mid '90s interested in
privacy technology and electronic cash
who were posting technical comments on a
on a cybunks and cryptography list using
remers. So already there were anonymous
participants. So this there's some kind
of precedent for that kind of way to
engage. But in any case, I think it's um
convenient and actually valuable for
Bitcoin that we don't know who the
founder is because a lot of mainstream
media tends to look for, you know, the
CEO or the leader and have the
impression that if they could just
persuade that person that they could
change the system to benefit their
business or something like that. So now
the fact that there's nobody to identify
and that Bitcoin is you know
decentralized chaotic there's no you
know there's no individual you can't
talk to the miners you can't talk to
developers you can't talk to other
companies none of them can make a change
it's really a a free market uh type of
situation where the market decides
how it evolves so I think it's
convenient that we don't know who
Satoshi is actually
>> could it be a group of people because
how can one person be that smart.
>> Um, yeah, I mean that's one of the
theories. I think the code probably is
relatively uniform and people tend to
have different it might be some kind of
indications it was written by multiple
people different styles in different
area or something. So my guess is it's
one person you know and also you know if
there's a lot of people it's hard to
keep a secret you know if one person can
uh control information more carefully.
I'm already imagining our comment
section would be Satoshi pretending to
not know who is Satoshi.
>> It's just one person, but it's not me.
>> Okay.
>> Um I uh we interviewed an investor
yesterday who said that the probability
of Bitcoin going to zero is now pretty
much impossible. Well, what if we were
to hypothetically break the proofof work
consensus mechanism? How would that
happen?
Um
>> in theory
>> well the proofof work mechanism is quite
robust in the sense that it's using hash
functions and hash functions
historically have suffered from
uh mathematical degradations in their
security properties and then say you
know people used to use MD5
then there was some problems discovered
in it you applications and internet
protocols switched to SHA one and now
we're using SHA 2 Now it's interesting
to see that SHA1 even though it had some
minor problems would still be fine for
Bitcoin mining. And the reason is that
if there's a small advantage, say it
becomes two times as easy to mine, the
difficulty just doubles. And so you've
got this kind of graceful degradation
phenomena and it seems like relatively
unlikely based on what's happened with
previous hash function failures between
MD4, MD5, SHA1. So the history of how
they have you know slept on their
security properties is generally
gradual. So I think that it's hard to
envisage the proof of work part
like fundamentally breaking. I think the
and and you can always you know in a
worst case switch to a newer uh hash
function or something. There are some
newer ones now char 3 for example. But
um I think the sort of mathematical risk
is perhaps more on the digital
signatures or the quantum risk which
people like to talk about. But I think
even there there are you know newer
signature schemes which are secure even
with quantum computers and in my view
quantum computers are still a few
decades away quite early in their sort
of fundamentals research. So I think you
know you could make an analog between
current CPUs and GPUs with you know tens
of billions of transistors and a very
early experiments with digital circuits
using you know cathode ray tubes and
like a table with you know a number of a
number of transistor like electronics
right so it's really very very early
days because you know the quantum
computers the state-of-the-art is to
factoriize is the number 21, i.e. what
you would learn in primary school that 3
* 7 is 21. That's the state-of-the-art
of what they can factoriize. And even
there, they had to cheat and not have
any error correction. So the way that
they sort of simulated that is they
repeat the calculation 64,000 times and
then see what the average, you know, the
most probable answer is. Um whereas in a
real factorization
you know you you need to have the error
correction um as part of the system not
by repeating it because it's already a
lot of work without repetition.
We were talking to Mike Belshi at DAS
digital asset summit and he said well
the biggest risk would be quantum
computers attacking Satoshi's wallet
because it's a big amount of right
>> Bitcoin.
>> Yeah. I mean that is a transition
question that you know if if this
happens within a couple of decades the
ecosystem will have to reach consensus
on. But I think of the two outcomes that
you know somebody with access to a
expensive quantum computer at that point
in a couple of decades
if nothing changes they might be able to
take lost coins or Satoshi's coins if he
doesn't move them you know if he's not
still around. So you know in my mind
what what would probably be the likely
approach would be to introduce a quantum
ready signature mechanism say in the
next decade and then people have a
decade to move ahead of that but some
people have clearly just lost their coin
their keys right and you know we don't
know if Satoshi is alive or not to to
move them right so I guess we'll find
out basically and then so I think
probably the better direction would be
to deprecate the uh
um to to deprecate the previous uh
system now. So I think the the likely
direction would be to deprecate the
ECDSA and signatures so that you can't
spend coins in that way. So that would
mean after people had had you know a
decade to migrate to a quantum ready
signature setup uh they wouldn't be able
to spend and so they would effectively
be frozen. say um you know it's a
delicate topic because people don't want
their money to be frozen but if the
alternative is you know economic chaos
from somebody taking them that's
probably a less bad outcome.
>> We had um a gentleman here um for our
first day as an interviewee. He's a big
Bitcoiner and he told us that what one
of the reasons that he became a
Bitcoiner or what convinced him to
become a Bitcoiner was in the early days
when the Silk Road project was shut
down, the government found the server
and shut that down, but they could not
shut down Bitcoin even if they had
attempted to. Can you just explain to
the layman who not who may not be very
technical why a centralized authority
may have failed and why that's not
really technically possible today? Well,
I mean, I think it's because Bitcoin is
um decentralized. So, if you look at
that digiccast system that I mentioned
in the mid '90s, there was one company
operating it. So, you know, the
government or the authorities could go
to them and say, you know,
>> but you couldn't in theory find every
node and shut that down.
>> Well, I mean, there's too many of them.
And it's also reactive, right? So, I
think there are like 100,000 nodes and
you don't really know from looking at
the network which ones are economically
active.
Um, and you don't know who's running
them. There's nodes on the internet and
so
um, and people are running them to for
their own economic benefit, right? To
validate the transactions they're doing.
So, yeah, I think, you know,
changing the nodes won't work because,
you know, people will just start their
own node. So, it's sort of reactive,
right? Uh, you know, if you shot if you
shot one down, 10 more appear or
something. And if it's so widespread,
you know, 100,000 nodes or it becomes a
million nodes, it's, you know, you're
you're fighting against windmills or
something as the thing is, right? You
know if if you have a few companies you
can push them legally you know
establishment governments courts but if
you've got you know 100 million users a
million nodes and they feel that this is
their you know natural right to have
hard money and you know not not be
interfered with you can't really stop
them ultimately.
>> Can I just add another 200 million nodes
then now I outnumber you.
Um well I think the the thing is and and
that arose in the sense that at some
point in Bitcoin's history people added
nodes to try and indicate support for
like a fork or something. But I think
the thing that that is the balance is
that the nodes are only really uh
economically significant if they have a
user behind them that is transacting. So
you know what what you're saying is
correct that in a distributed system
where you don't have identity you have
the simple attack which means that
somebody could pretend to be a thousand
people or a million people and you know
if you have a system that's designed
badly that could confuse or overwhelm
the system but in in a Bitcoin model
what matters is actually the economic
nodes or the economic weight of the
nodes. So you know if a particular node
is a payment processor or an exchange
that one's carrying a lot of economic
weight because they are verifying a lot
of value daily um but you know if an
individual's running a node that's
verifying the transactions that they do
or their savings and that kind of thing
so it's a bit indirect but I think those
economic nodes are the more important
ones than the sheer number. So most
people are running it for a reason,
which is, you know, they have a wallet
and they're using their own node or
something like that.
>> But running a node has no financial
incentive.
>> Uh, no, you don't get paid for it. It's
a more of um sort of self-protective in
incentive. So it's a bit like a say in
gold. So you receive a gold payment, you
want to check the gold is, you know,
authentic, it's pure gold. And so you
will, you know, use some essay method
or, you know, go to an expert to check
for gold. In Bitcoin, the way you do
that is you you run a node and it tells
you this is a real Bitcoin transaction
where if you go through a service
provider or third party, you're relying
on them to do that. And so you don't
really know for yourself, right? So a
lot of people want to, you know, have
that bit of extra security for
themselves by running a node so they
know they've saved their own coins. So
it's that kind of the value is indirect.
It's uh you know verifying your coins.
Um and you know not everybody has to do
that because there are you know hundreds
of thousands of other people doing it
directly and you know millions and
millions of people doing it indirectly
via different wallets and exchanges and
things like that.
>> So Bitcoin having affects the price
perfectly. You you can look at the chart
it looks perfect. Well if everybody
knows that why don't people just buy
early? Yeah, that's a good question and
you can see it's a
it's a kind of arbitrage rate. So I
think actually the reason is a bit
sophisticated which is that it's hard to
arbitrage something which is volatile.
So the thought experiment I was saying
is what if in a given country the
government reduces the taxation on
rental properties
>> they cut it in half you know to give
people a month's notice. It's going to
get cut in half. As soon as the news
comes that you know in in a month or two
the tax is going to be half the resale
value of rental properties will jump
immediately because house prices or
apartments are relatively stable
pricing. Now with Bitcoin of course
everybody knows there's a hing coming at
a date you know actually a few years in
advance right so let's say it's 6 months
before the h havinging why don't people
arbitrage that I think the reason is
that you know if they are not uh bitcoin
exposed they're trying to do it on a
dollar basis they could see that it
might have an impact on the on the price
but the timing is a bit uncertain you
know the price tends to move a bit after
the hovering and you know let's say they
think they can make a 50% % profit from
this if they if they do it right. They
might be worried that you know they buy
it but the price is moving around at 40%
volatility per year. So they might lose
the the 50%. And so they'd have that
uncertainty, right? So I think that
volatility makes it harder to uh you
know to to arbitrage that
event you can see is coming because
normally um markets try to price things
in as soon as the information is known
and information is priced in. So I think
it's a good question and I think the
volatility is something to do with why
it doesn't get priced in. I think
another reason can be that we know about
a haring but there's a lot of people who
are looking at it from the outside who
don't know a lot of the details right so
it's obvious to us but maybe it's not so
obvious to the market you know you would
think how could somebody hold Bitcoin
and not know about the hing but they
probably do and you know they're looking
at the financial news shows which you
know are getting more sophisticated in
their commentary these days but going
back a few years they would sort of look
at Bitcoin news and draw like the wrong
market conclusion for it. And then you
know people who are kind of sitting on
the outside look at their news and react
to it and sort of create
um market opportunities for people who
understood the market better.
>> Don't don't share this interview. Don't
spoil our secrets. Keep markets
inefficient for the people who do know.
>> That's your conclusion.
>> Yes. Well, I would like to move on to
the future of finance that runs on
Bitcoin, which is coincidentally the
name of your panel that you did or not
panel but the keynote speech that you
did here at the Bitcoin Las Vegas
conference. Tell us about the future of
Binance.
>> Well, I think it's an interesting time
for um you know, next wave of Bitcoin
adoption, which is the early stages of
the institutions, the easier access to
the Bitcoin market via ETFs. For a lot
of people, the way they deal with their
investments is they call their broker or
financial advisor. So the ETFs give them
a way to do that. You see the early
stages of uh fund managers allocating
Bitcoin into uh diversified
funds. Um most recently Black Rockck um
made a recommendation for a 2%
allocation to a diversified portfolio.
Um but I think the proportion of managed
funds in Bitcoin is still extremely low.
So I think that's yet to happen. They
they have a a kind of careful methodical
process about how they would you know
bring something to market. So it might
take some months before they actually
act on it and start to make it available
to different segments of their uh
investor clients. And then I think the
other thing that's evolving is Bitcoin
the asset class in terms of its
technological handling is starting to
interface to traditional finance. So one
way it does that is via custodians. So
we're seeing more institutional level
custodians come in. Blockstream made an
investment in Blockstream Capital
Partners made an investment in Kmenu
which is an institutional grade
custodian for that reason. And the
recent uh regulatory improvements in the
US make it easier for um the larger
established
uh custodians of shares and bonds to
actually enter the Bitcoin custody
market. So they're not in market yet,
but they don't the the regulatory hurdle
that made it difficult for them is now
lifted. And so that might be another way
that it makes it easier in the future
for managed uh managed funds to
participate in Bitcoin because they'll
be able to do it via a custodian that
they already work with, let's say. Um
and then the other part of it is using
Bitcoin layer 2s like liquid which are
um sort of bringing the bearer
settlement and simple smart contracted
advantages of the Bitcoin network which
is the most robust of of the networks
available right so I think it's sort of
showing that Bitcoin can be an internet
for money but also an internet for
assets and so on liquid we have a number
of different assets about 3.3 billion
Um now one of the new newer additions is
securitized
um
shares which are interesting to
Bitcoiners. So kind of crossover assets.
So namely the treasury companies so far
Micro Strategy and Meta Planet but more
in the future. And what happens there is
you know there is a a custodian that
holds the underlying shares. the token
you're buying is a security. So, you
have to enroll in order to to buy and
receive it in a wallet. A a recent uh
phenomena on on liquid is the
introduction of crossover assets. So,
shares that are uh Bitcoin correlated in
some way. And so the first two obviously
Micro Strategy being the first major
treasury company in a public company
format and then also um Meta Planet more
recently and and the interesting thing
you know it's a security so you have to
enroll to be able to buy it and transact
it in a wallet. Um you can hold it in a
wallet. It's a very Bitcoin-l like
experience on the liquid network, you
know, with seeds and you can sort of pay
somebody, you know, a hundth of a micro
strategy share to sell a lunch bill.
It's around $4, let's say 33 375 $4. And
uh you can also trade in a 24x7 market
sort of OTC non-custodial market. And uh
that's this market is actually Bitcoin
denominated and on a weekend it can
achieve you know it's achieved a similar
volume to the Frankfurt ADR on Micro
Strategy. U but it's the only market
that's open and it's Bitcoin denominated
which is an interesting way to trade the
Treasury ST shares. in effect a kind of
Bitcoin basis relative value trade where
you're looking at you know the relative
value between Bitcoin and a treasury
company so that you might buy it when
the MNAV like the market cap compared to
the net asset value of the Bitcoin they
hold is low and then sell it later when
it's higher and buy back Bitcoin at a
higher price and where your objective is
to um increase slightly the amount of
Bitcoin that you had before you way into
the trade. So, you can see that this
market is a bit one-sided. They there
are clearly Bitcoin traders in there,
but there's a bit of variation and you
know, even for traditional investors who
are not looking at this trade on a
Bitcoin basis, it's a 24x7 market. So,
it fills in some of the gaps where you
know, you've got particularly with the
Japanese one from Europe that, you know,
that market starts at 2 a.m. that's
quite difficult to interact with. And
some of these markets have market halts.
So the Japanese market is generally
halting when the price gets moves more
than 15% of the day. And so you've seen
a sort of difference in price between
the US ADR for better planet from the
Japanese market. And so you know 24 by7
market can help uh smooth that out and
give more global access. I think
sometimes people find it difficult to
get access to um shares on on markets
outside their jurisdiction.
I'm just wondering what does your day
look like
>> cuz you know everything.
>> It's a lot of fun. Too many toys to play
with. Right. So, I'm quite interested in
uh trading and investment from the mid
'90s. So, Bitcoin presented um you know,
as well as a kind of technical interest
in electronic cash. I would say those
previous electronic cash systems were
more what we would call stable coins
today. You know, people were expecting
to be able to if they got deployed to be
able to wire money in, get some
electronic money in euros or dollars or
what have you, transact that in a bare
form online, and eventually be able to
cash that in, you know, back into a bank
account where Bitcoin is more of a gold
competitor. So, it has a an investment
component. And of course, the adoption
story as it as it gains use is is what's
driving it. I think eventually it will
reach you know full adoption. We don't
know where that will be. You know
>> what does that look like?
>> What does full adoption look like? So I
think the you know one target is gold
and you know gold values are quite high
at the moment because of the macro hedge
phenomena where governments will buy
gold in times of uncertainty and so but
even there with the current Bitcoin
price level uh it's within about a
factor of nine of reaching the gold
market cap and then the larger
addressable market for monetary premiums
in different assets like housing there's
a lot of monetary premium there where
people will buy an apartment and not use
it, not even rent it out just as an
investment vehicle, right? So you see a
lot of underused housing premium in the
housing sector in different countries
and obviously premium in shares in the
stock markets and bonds and other forms
of alternative assets. And so you know
how Finny actually estimated that to be
200 trillion and like surprisingly he
did this in like I think 10th of January
2009 before there are any transactions
and any market value. So it's quite a
kind of forward-looking estimate but it
seems to be still you know considered a
reasonable estimate of the size of that
addressable market. Now we don't know
you know how much of that Bitcoin will
capture. So there's a bit of conjecture
there, but it seems logical that you
know if the institutional adoption
continues and the retail interest
continues that Bitcoin could get there.
>> Let's talk about that prediction. So
that was a long time ago and I'm
assuming people were shocked at that
number back then.
>> Well, right, it was very fanciful
because there were no users. I think he
received the first transaction ever from
uh uh Soshi and I think that was I'm not
sure if he got that transaction before
he made that comment or after but it may
was even before any got that
transaction. I believe he got it in
block nine. So you know probably he sent
this comment after he received a
transaction. So this this is just what
we learned afterwards, right? I wasn't
uh paying attention during this time
>> January 09.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so I mean it was such a
wild prediction that I think people
would look at that as you know a kind of
imagination hypothetical right because I
think the you know the probability that
the network would catch on users would
use it and a and a price would form that
there would be venues exchange platforms
you could trade it on those were all
years away at that point in fact so
there's a lot of uncertainty whether it
would get there even
>> I I don't have a question that could top
that. Let's let's end it here. That was
a great end uh to the conversation.
Thank you very much, Adam, Dr. Beck.
Pleasure meeting you.
>> Thanks for having me on.
>> Such a great chat.
Thanks.